Finding Aid for the Warren Taylor Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Warren Taylor Collection
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0436
1.26 linear feet
- Correspondence - Outgoing - 4 holograph letters (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Incoming - 49 letters, 8post cards and 2 greeting cards alphabetically arranged. These letters are typescript and holograph with 3 xerox copies (the Edgar Hill Duncan letters). (Box 1)
- Essays - These 18 essays were done in 1922-1923 while Taylor was a student at Vanderbilt. They have notes on them by his professors, John Crowe Ransom and Walter Clyde Curry. (Box 1)
- Lectures - 18 lectures prepared by Taylor while at Oberlin College, 1939-1971 (Box 1)
- Poems - 30 typescript, holograph and carbon copies. These poems circulated among the fugitives in the 1920's. There are 9 by John Paul Abbott, 1 by J. Comfort, 1 by Merrill Moore, 2 by Charles Moss, 3 by Allen Tate, 4 by Robert Penn Warren and 9 unsigned. (Box 1)
- Photographs - 2 photographs of John Crowe Ransom. One was taken in 1948 while he spoke in the Baltimore Museum of Art. The other is undated and was probably taken at Kenyon College. (Box 1)
- Theater Programs - 32, dated from 1921 to 1932 and chronologically arranged. Most of these programs are from the Orpheum Theatre and the Ryman Auditorium, Nashville, Tennessee. (Box 2)
- Musical Programs - 55, dated from 1922 to 1931 and chronologically arranged. Programs mostly from Ryman Auditorium and Ward-Belmont Conservatory of Music, Nashville, Tennessee. Also included are 16 programs from the Nashville Symphony Orchestra, dating from 1921-1927. (Box 2)
- Pamphlet - The Golden Mean and Other Poems, by Ridley Wills and Allen Tate. 31 pages in length, contains poems by Ridley Wills, Allen Tate and Merrill Moore, published in 1923. (Box 2)
- Magazine - Poetry, A Magazine of Verse, edited by Harriet Monroe. May, 1932 issue edited by Allen Tate. Includes contributions by Donald Davidson, Merrill Moore, Allen Tate, and Robert Penn Warren. (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings - 7 short columns "The 10 Worst Books I Ever Read" written by Jesse Wills, Allen Tate, Robert Penn Warren, Warren Taylor, Lawrence Blair and Elsie Warren Stokes. Reviews of plays (8) presented at the Ryman Auditorium and the Orpheum Theatre, Nashville. Also included is an article from the Cleveland Plain Dealer about Ransom. These clippings are not dated except for the article about Ransom and the name of the newspaper is not usually given. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous - Material includes a program of the Vanderbilt Semi-Centennial Pageant, Oct. 16, 1925; an announcement of a public reading during a reunion of the Fugitive Poets at Vanderbilt, May 4, 1956; a book cover from The World’s Body by John Crowe Ransom; a list of publications of Warren Taylor 1937-1972; 7 canceled checks signed by Robert Penn Warren as treasurer for the Fugitive; bibliography for one of Taylor's classes at Oberlin and outline of the course content; note card with a poem by Merrill Moore printed on one side and a short message by Moore on reverse; periodical Avenue, dated July 23, 1934, containing William S. Knickerbocker's review of I’ll Take My Stand. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous – (see addendum) (Box 3)
- Addendum
  - Articles (Box 3)
  - Knickerbocker, William S. “The Fugitives of Nashville.” Sewanee Review, 36 (1928), 211-24. (Box 3)
  - Ransom, John Crowe. “The South--Old of New?” Sewanee Review, 36 (1928), 139-47. (Box 3)
  - Tate, Allen. “American Poetry Since 1920.” The Bookman, 68 (1929), 503-08. (Box 3)
  - -----------. “Last Days of the Charming Lady.“ The Nation, 121 (1925), 485-86. (Box 3)
  - -----------. “Poetry and the Absolute.” Sewanee Review, 35 (1927), 41-52. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Incoming (Box 3)
  - Tate, Allen, (1), Feb. 14, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 3)
  - Jack, Peter Monro. “A New Collection of Poems by Allen Tate.” Rev. of The Mediterranean and Other Poems. New York Times, 16 August 1936. (Box 3)
  - Allen Tate obituary picture in unidentified newspaper, 9 Feb. 1979. (Box 3)
  - Notes (Box 3)
  - 2 folders on Tate; 1 includes published poems labeled “not collected” 1 folder on Agrarians (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Biographical sketch on dustjacket of Tate’s Poems, 1928-1931 (Box 3)
  - Essay (Box 3)
  - Sanborn, Herbert. “Philosophies and Psychologies.” Read at the annual meeting of the Southern Society for Philosophy and Psychology, Washington University, 4 April 1947. Inscribed by Sanborn. (Box 3)
  - Lectures - Prepared while at Oberlin College, 1939-1971 (Box 1)
    - American and Un-American Activities, (May 20, 1947) (Box 1)
    - Democracy and the Oberlin Idea, (Jun. 10, 1950) (Box 1)
    - The Four Freedoms and the Cold War, (Mar. 30, 1949) (Box 1)
    - How to Beat Propaganda, (Dec. 19, 1940) (Box 1)
    - Humanism and Liberal Education (Box 1)
    - Lear and the Lost Self, (Sept. 25, 1961) (Box 1)
    - Learning and Labor, (May 11, 1948) (Box 1)
    - A Letter to Croce, (1954) (Box 1)
    - Liberal Education, Power, and Civilization, (Oct. 16, 1961) (Box 1)
    - Literature and Action, (May 3, 1944) (Box 1)
    - Literature and General Education, (2 copies, n.d.) (Box 1)
    - Literature, Science, and Man (Box 1)
    - Noon and Babylonian Starlight, (Dec. 8, 1939) (Box 1)
    - On Being An American, (1971) (Box 1)
    - The Place of Literature in the Realm of Values, (n.d.) (Box 1)
    - The Promise of American Education, (n.d.) (Box 1)
    - Shakespeare’s Tragic Heroes, (n.d.) (Box 1)
    - What is Propaganda, (Dec. 6, 1940) (Box 1)
  - Poems, 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Abbott, John Paul (Box 1)
      April
      A Child’s Laugh
      End of a Story
      The Grey World
      Night on a Barrier Island
      Night - Three Quatrains
      An Old Pedant Speaks
      Red Birds
      When Fairies Dance
      Untitled poem
    - Comfort, J. (Box 1)
      Febuary Snow
    - Moore, Merrill (Box 1)
      Romance and Realism 5:30 P.M.
    - Moss, Charles (Box 1)
      To Rupert Brooke, The Lover
      Travelers
    - Tate, Allen (Box 1)
      Death of Little Boys
      Sudden Face
      Young Classicist to a Younger Romantic Friend
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 1)
      Crusade
      A Queen Mother to Her Twin Sons
      Wild Oats
      Wrestling Match
  - Correspondence - Outgoing (Box 1)
    - Oct. 27, 1977; Nov. 17, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Dec. 16, 1977; Feb. 6, 1978, Edgar Hill Duncan (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Incoming (Box 1)
  - Bandy, Bill, (1), Jun. 24; ? (to Pierre ?) (Box 1)
  - Curry, Walter Clyde, (1), Jan. 11, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Donald, (43), May 8, 1925; Feb. 17 Mar. 11, Aug. 28, Oct. 12, Nov. 22, Nov, 29, 1926; Jan. 16, Apr. 17, Sept. 28, Nov. 2, 1927; Feb. 13, Feb. 29,' Apr. 3, Apr. 10, Apr. 23, Apr. 26, May 3, May 12, May 24, May 25, Jim. 20,. Aug. 22, Oct. 29, Nov. 23, 1928; Mar. 26, Apr. 9, Nov. 27, 1929; Nov. 26, Dec. 28, 1930; Sept. 16, 1933; Apr. 25, 1954; Apr. 17, ?; Apr. 27, ?; Aug. 20, ?; Sept. 29, ?; Oct. 13, ?; Oct. 15, ?; 3 letters n.d.; 2 Christmas cards, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Duncan, Edgar Hill, (3), Nov. 15, Dec. 2, 1977; Feb. 1, 1978; (xerox copies) (Box 1)
  - Lytle, Andrew Nelson, (2), n.d.; Apr. 7, 1923; (enclosed in this letter is a poem by Lytle A Reflection in french and english) (Box 1)
  - Mims, Edwin, (1), Apr. 8, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Merrill, (2), May 18, 1935; Jun. 29, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, (2), May 1, 1933; Mar. 28, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Tate, Allen, (2), Sept. 11, 1926; Aug. 20, ? (Box 1)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Zobou, Bessie J., (1), Nov. 7, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Essays - Taylor’s student work 1922-1923, with comments by John Crowe Ransom and Walter Clyde Curry (Box 1)
    About Charteris
    The Bohemian of Rue Morne
    Casanova in Wisconsin
    George Gordon Byron
    Greek Tragedy
    In Time of Waste
    Joseph Hergesheimer
    Mr. Prohack
    Mr. Robinson, Lancelot and Merlin (2 copies)
    Old Wives Tale
    Philosophy and Dramas of Schiller
    Poor Children
    Professor With Umbrella
    Retrogression and Willa Cather
    Robert Frost
    A Shropshire Lad Grown Up
    Toward an Anatomy of Criticism
    The Way of All Flesh (2 copies)
  - Unsigned (Box 1)
    After the Storm
    August Revival: Crosby Junction
    Dementa (Lowenstein, is penciled at top of page)
    Letter of a Mother
    One, Two, Three
    Simple
    The Story the Idiot Tried to Tell
    To One Awake
    Untitled
  - Photographs - 2 photographs of John Crowe Ransom. One was taken in 1948 while he spoke in the Baltimore Museum of Art. The other is undated and was probably taken at Kenyon College. (Box 1)
  - Theatre Programs (Box 2)
    - 19 Programs from the Orpheum Theatre 1921-1925(Nashville) (Box 2)
    - Lombardi, Ltd. (Hazele Burgess Players), Nov. 28, 1921 (Box 2)
    - Dec. 19, 1921 - Little Women (Hazele Brugess Players) (Box 2)
    - Stop Thief (Hazele Burgess Players), Dec. 26, 1921 (Box 2)
    - Jan. 2, 1922, The Love of Su Shong (The Burgess Players) (Box 2)
    - The Eyes of Youth (Burgess Players), Jan. 9, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Mary Rose (Ruth Chatterton), 1922 (Box 2)
    - 1922, Shakespearean Repertoire (Robert B. Mantell) (Box 2)
    - The Humming Bird (Clara Joel and the Orpheum Players), May 26, 1924 (Box 2)
    - The Man Who Came Back (Clara Joel and the Orpheum Players, Jun. 2, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Within the Law (Clara Joel and the Orpheum Players, Jun. 9, 1924 (Box 2)
    - The Thief of Bagdad (Douglas Fairbanks), Oct. 27, 1924 (Box 2)
    - The Student Prince in Heidelberg, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Blind Youth (Lou Teilegen), n.d. (Box 2)
    - The Covered Wagon (Paramount picture), n.d. (Box 2)
    - Al. G. Fields’ Minstrels, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Turn to the Right (Hazele Burgess Players), n.d. (Box 2)
    - The Big Parade (John Gilbert), n.d. (Box 2)
    - The Merchant of Venice (Robert B. Mantell and Genevieve Hamper), n.d. (Box 2)
    - The Merchant of Venice and Richard III (Robert Mantell and Genevieve Hamper), n.d. (Box 2)
    - 13 Programs, 1922-1932 (Box 2)
    - Grand Opening of Capitol Theatre, movie Let’s Get Married, Apr. 19, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Ryman Auditorium, Mr. Walter Hampden in Repertoire, Jan. 16, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Ryman Auditorium, Fritz Leiber, Nov. 13, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Ryman Auditorium, Faust (San Carlo Grand Opera Company), Jan. 5, 1925 (Box 2)
    - The Little Theatre Guild, An Evening of One Act Plays, Apr. 26, 1926 (Box 2)
    - The Little Theatre Guild, The Imaginary Invalid, Apr. 17, 1926 (Box 2)
    - The Little Theatre Guild, To the Ladies, May 13, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Vagabond Players, Time is a Dream, Aug. 1, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Centennial Club, Celebration of Moliere, Apr. 26, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Hedda Gabler, directed by Hale Shaneberger, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Calumet Players, Four one act plays, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Faust, (Francis Robinson) Neely Auditorium 2 copies, Apr. 7, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Rosmersholm, (The Devereux Dramatic Co.) at Peabody College, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Musical Programs (Box 2)
    - Erna Rubinstein - Violinist Ward-Belmont Conservatory of Music, Mar. 22, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Frieda Hempel - Vocalist Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 27, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Amelita Galli-Curci - Vocalist Ryman Auditorium, May 8, 1922 (Box 2)
    - La Boheme Ryman Auditorium, May 18, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Madame Emma Calve - Vocalist Ryman Auditorium, Feb. 19, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Ganna Walska - Vocalist Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 1, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Irene Castle Variety Ryman Auditorium, Oct. 13, 1923 (Box 2)
    - San. Carlo Grand Opera Co. La Traviata and La Boheme - Ryman Auditorium, Oct. 19, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Ruth St. Denis and Ted Shawn Ryman Auditorium, Dec. 14, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Roland Hayes - Tenor Ryman Auditorium, Dec. 15, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Paderewski Ryman Auditorium, Feb. 6, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Anna Povlowa Ryman Auditorium, Feb. 27, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Blossom Time Orpheum, Mar. 24, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Chicago Opera Artists Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 26, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Blossom Time (2 copies) Orpheum Theatre, Oct. 9, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Vladimir De Pachmann - Pianist Ryman Auditorium, Nov. 17, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Mischa Levitzki - Pianist Ryman Auditorium, Feb. 19, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Jascha Heifetz Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 9, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Rudolph Ganz and the St. Louis Symphony Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 20, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Cortese Trio Concert Ryman Auditorium, Apr. 16, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Vratislar Murdoch - Violinist Ryman Auditorium, Apr. 27, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Sadye Brown - Pianist Houck’s Auditorium, May 4, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Joseph T. MacPherson - Vocalist Ryman Auditorium, May 5, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Ballet Russe Ryman Auditorium, Nov. 21, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Rudolph Ganz - Pianist Ryman Auditorium, Nov. 30, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Miss Frieda Hempel Ryman Auditorium, Jan. 18, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Mischa Elman - Violinist Ryman Auditorium, Mar. 19, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Giovanni Martinelli (Metropolitian Opera) Ryman Auditorium, Apr. 16, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Vesper Concert at Vanderbilt, Jun. 6, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Marion Talley (Metropolitian Opera) Ryman Auditorium, Jun. 10, 1926 (Box 2)
    - No No Nanette Orpheum, Oct. 2, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Spring Concert - Music Study Club Hotel Andrew Jackson Ball-Room, May 12, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra Ryman Auditorium, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Nashville Symphony Orchestra Programs (Box 2)
    - 1st Season, 3rd Concert, Jan. 30, 1921 (Box 2)
    - 2nd Season, all 6 concert programs bound together, 1921 - 1922 (Box 2)
    - 3rd Season, 1st Concert, Oct. 15, 1922 (Box 2)
    - 3rd Season, 2nd Concert, Nov. 19, 1922 (Box 2)
    - 3rd Season, 6th Coneert, Apr. 15, 1923 (Box 2)
    - 5th Season, 3rd Concert, Feb. 10, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 5th Season, 4th Concert, Mar. 15, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 5th Season, 5th Concert, Apr. 19, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 5th Season, 6th Concert, May 10, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 1st Concert, Nov. 8, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 2nd Concert, Dec. 13, 1925 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 3rd Concert, Jan. 17, 1926 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 4th Concert, Feb. 10, 1926 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 5th Concert, Mar. 14, 1926 (Box 2)
    - 6th Season, 6th Concert, Apr. 25, 1926 (Box 2)
    - 7th Season, 5th Concert, Mar. 13, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlet (Box 2)
  - The Golden Mean and Other Poems, 31 pages Poems by Ridley Wills,'Allen Tate and Merrill Moore (Box 2)
  - Magazine (Box 2)
  - Poetry A Magazine of Verse, May, 1932. Includes Contributions by Donald Davidson, Merrill Moore, Allen Tate and Robert Penn Warren (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
  - 7 short columns “The 10 Worst Books I Ever Read”, by Jesse Wills, Warren Taylor, Allen Tate, Robert Penn Warren, Lacy Lockert, Lawrence Blair and Elsie Warren Stokes, n.d. (Box 2)
  - 8 reviews of plays presented at the Ryman Auditorium and Orpheum Theatre, Nashville, n.d. (Box 2)
  - An article from the Cleveland Plain Dealer about John Crowe Ransom., (Nov. 30, 1952) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Program of Vanderbilt’s Semi-Centennial Pageant, Oct. 16, 1925; an announcement of a public reading during the reunion of the Fugitive Poets at Vanderbilt, May 4, 1956; a book cover from The World’s Body by John Crowe Ransom; a list of publications by Warren Taylor, 1937-1972; a bibliography for one of Taylor’s classes at Oberlin and outline for the course; 7 canceled checks dated Apr.-May 1923 and signed by Robert Penn Warren as treasurer of the Fugitive; note card with a poem by Merrill Moore on reverse; 8 page periodical Avenue, dated Jul. 23, 1934 containing William S. Knickerbocker’s review of I’ll Take My Stand (Box 2)